Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Appendix: Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Identified or Acquired 1978-1990.
  - The Charles E. Young Research Library: Department of Special Collections.
    - Giunta Publishing House, stock book. Florence., ca. 1600-1610; 170/622.; Paper, 309 ff.; Bound in a limp leather wrapper, contemporary fore-edge tabs, s. XVI.
      Acquired from H.P. Kraus in 1982.
    - Planctus Mariae. Italy., s. XIV; 170/623.; Parchment. A fragment of a roll.
      Acquired from B. Rosenthal in 1986.
    - Archimedes, trans. by Federico Commandino, etc. Rome., s. XVIImed; 1553; 170/624.; Paper, 218 ff. A composite manuscript made up of three parts. The Commandino manuscript served as the printer's copy for the Aldine edition of 1558.; Bound in antique calf.
      Belonged to the Albani Library (with arms of Pope Clement XI, 1700-1721).
      Acquired from Maggs in 1986.
      A substantial portion of the Albani Library is at Catholic University of America in Washington, D.C.
    - Jerome Cusatus, Fastorum libri xii. Rome(?)., ca. 1525-1535; 170/626.; Paper, 230 ff. Apparently the author's fair copy in his own hand, with numerous corrections on slips of paper neatly pasted in.; Bound in quarter leather gilt and marble paper over pasteboards; edges uncut.
      The work correlates the liturgical calendar with the zodiac.
      Belonged to Frederick North, fifth earl of Guilford (1766-1827) (bookplate). His library, largely collected in Italy, was sold in eight London sales 1828-1835.
      Purchased with many others by Sir Thomas Phillipps (his number on printed paper label, 7459).
      Acquired from Maggs (catalog no. 1066, #86) in 1986.
    - Niccolo di Antonio da Fiesso di Ferrara, Meditationes super passionem Christi; Epide beate Marie virginis ad universos Christi fideles. Ferrara., s. XVmed; 170/627.; Parchment, 60 ff. Humanist script. Illuminated initial on fol. I restored.; Bound in paper boards, s. XIX.
      Belonged to the Carthusians of St. Christopher near Ferrara (ex libris); this house was Cistercian until 1454, then Carthusian.
    - Hours of the Virgin, Use of Utrecht. Delft., s. XV; 170/630.; Parchment, 168 ff. 8 initials with characteristic delicate penwork; with peacock on f. 15; places for animals later initials left blank. Written by the Augustinian nuns of St. Agnes in Delft.; Bound in niger morocco.
      Belonged to Arthur Barry Smith (1843-1925) in 1893 (ex libris).
      Acquired from P. Priages in 1986.
      Another manuscript from this scriptorium in Greater Los Angeles is Huntington HM 1127, and a third is owned by R.H. Rouse and M.A. Rouse.
    - Heinrich Seuse (Suso), Horologe de sapience, French translation by Joan de Souhabe. Southwest France., s. XVex; 1389; 170/633.; Paper, 223 ff.; Bound in contemporary whittawed skin over paper boards with two fore-edge ties.
      Probably belonged to Anne de Polignac (1495-1554), wife of Francois II de La Rochefoucauld.
      Château de La Roche-Guyon sale Paris, Hotel Drouot (2 July 1927) no.6.
      Acquired from B. Rosenthal in 1987.
    - Aelius Aristeides, Oratio de urbe Roma, translated from Greek by Scipione Forteguerri [Carteromachus]. Rome(?)., between 1507 and 1513; 170/634.; Paper, 18 ff. Written by Francesco Baroncini. Unbound. Formerly ff. 203-220 of a larger volume.
      Apparently the only known manuscript of the Latin translation of this oration. Forteguerri (1466-1515) was a pupil of Politian and a collaborator with Aldus Manutius, for whom he prepared numerous texts for publication. He was important in establishing the Academy in 1502 and from 1504 lived in Rome; he dedicated this translation to Cardinal Galeotto della Rovere (d. 11 September 1507) into whose service he had entered after leaving Venice. Printed in the second edition of the Scriptores historiae augustae, Venice, 1519.
      Early modern provenance unknown.
      Acquired from B. Rosenthal in 1988.
    - St. Antoninus of Florence, Summula confessionis. Fondi (S. Italy)., 1478; 170/635.; Paper, 140 ff. Written by Antonio de Capitalibus at the abbey of S. Onofrio in Fondi.; Bound in contemporary Italian bare wooden boards, remains of two fore-edge clasps.
      Apparently copied from the edition printed by Johann de Colonia and Johann Manthen in Venice in 1474 or that of 1477.
      Acquired from Maggs in 1988.
    - Antonio Beccadelli (Panormita), Alfonsi regis epistolae, Aifonsi regis legationes. Italy., s. XV2; 170/638.; Paper, 72 ff. + 10 ff. Written by one person in an italic hand. Final letter added by a contemporary hand. Lacking final leaf or leaves.; Bound in contemporary Italian calf, crudely rebacked; remains of a single fore-edge clasp front to back.; Numerous early signatures and pen trials crossed out: “Iste per me bade.. .,” “Josephus... 20,” “Vincentii Morsi liber emptus #20,” “Mandastini (?) achama.. .,' “D'AIoysi d'Her... lo,” and following the colophon: “domini Andree & amicorum codex.”
      Acquired from B. Rosenthal in 1989.
    - Collectanea:Vitae patrum (1 f. missing after f. 58); musical scale; Lotario da Segni, De miseria condicionis humanae; unidentified text, incomplete (8 ff. missing after f. 82); Hugh of St. Victor, Soliloquium de arrha animae; Johannes Herrolt, Sermones. West Germany., 1476-1478; 170/642.; Paper. 180 ff. Written by John of Tübingen, subdeacon of the Cistercian abbey of Salem near Heidelberg (f. 58v, “Per me fratrum Johannem de Tuibingen sacer professus in Salem isto tempore subdiaconus anno domini 1478”). Attractive large floral initial on blue ground; space for initials left unfinished.; Bound in deer skin over wooden boards, s. XV; fragments of medieval manuscripts, one in German, used as pastedowns and quire reinforcement.
      Belonged, presumably, to the Cistercians of Salem abbey near Uberlingen until the dissolution.
      Names: “Johannes Krantz,” “Stephanus Hegar 1452.”
    - Alexander of Villedieu, Doctrinale. Italy (Venice?)., s. XVex; 170/643.; Paper, 37 ff. Signed by the scribe “Ludovicus” (”Scriptor sum tails demonstrat littera qualis nomen non pono quia Ludovicum laudare nolo. Amen”). Opening page with floral border and heraldic device; 58 illuminated initials of which 33 are unfinished.; Bound in tree calf (s. XVIII/ XIX), rubbed. With the arms of a member of the Orio and Contarini families of Venice (heraldic device f. 1).
      Given to the Cistercian abbey of San Bartolo in Ferrara by 1546 (ff. 2, 37v “Questo libro sie dela abbadia di san bartholo appresso ferrara MDXLVI”).
      Acquired by the abbey of Billy in Besancon (f. 1 ink stamp “Bibliotheca Billiana”).
      Belonged to Sir Thomas Phillipps, no.26059.
    - Peter Riga, Aurora. Northern Spain., s. XIIIin; 170/648.; Parchment, 58 ff. Quires of 8 leaves. 2 columns of 32 lines. Attractive pen work initials.; Bound in green morocco, s. XVIII.
      Medieval and early modern provenance unknown. Inscription “Corby Barrow, Lancaster, 1854,” Belonged to Sidney G. Hamilton, librarian of Hertford College, Oxford, his sale Sotheby's 25 July 1917, lot 4427; to Ronald Coates. From the library of Bent Juel-Jensen (book plate).
      Acquired from A. Thomas in 1989.
    - Lectern service book. Spain., s. XVI-XVIII; ***170/651.; Parchment, 300 ff.; Bound in leather over wooden boards, with metal bosses.
      A composite volume made up of portions of service books written at various dates, the largest portion written in 1591, other portions in 1676 and 1790.
      Belonged to a Franciscan house.
    - Lectern Gradual. Spain., 1539; ***170/652.; Parchment, 219 ff.; Bound in leather over heavy wooden boards with metal bosses and corner supports.
      Commissioned, according to an attestation at the end of the book, by Juan Fernandes de Paredes and Antonia Cornela his wife from Valladolid for the convent of Bernardine nuns of St. Mary at Avila at the request of his sister Francisca Fernandes, a nun of the convent, in return for prayers for his soul and those of his family. Written by Alonzo Sanchez of Valencia, writer of books in Valladolid, who finished it on 20 November 1539.
      Belonged to the Monastery of St. Mary in Avila until at least 1 August 1949. Given by Bert J. Brock sometime between then and 1963.
    - St. Athanasius of Alexandria, Contra gentiles, De incarnatione Verbi, Latin translation by Ambrogio Traversari (1386-1439), one of five known manuscripts. Italy., s. XV 2; 170/653.; Parchment, 76 ff. 29 long lines. Written by one person in a humanist hand.; Bound in dark blue straight grained morocco with gilt edges for H. Drury (see below) by Charles Lewis, s. XIXin.
      Written in Florence or more likely Venice after 1428.
      Belonged to the English collector Henry Drury (inscription and date 1824), his sale 1827 lot 400 to Cochrane. Sold by Maggs (cat. 967 [1975] no. 65).
      In the possession of a Dutch private collector. Acquired from B. Rosenthal in 1989 with the assistance of the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies.
    - Indulgentie, stationes et mirabilia urbis Rome, roll. Germany., s. XV1; 170/656.; Parchment, a roll made up of four sections sewn together. With ten by one person in a German hybrida with initials in red. Shelved in a box.
      Contains prayers to be said at the holy sites in Rome in three parts with an extensive listing of Roman churches and monuments. Presumably a pilgrim's roll, written in Germany at the beginning of the fifteenth century.
      Early modern provenance unknown. Acquired from B. Rosenthal in 1990 with the assistance of the Henry Bruman Foundation.
    - Register of the city of Volterra. Volterra., 1311; Collection 902, Box 533 no.i.; Paper (watermark), 1quire of 48 ff., foliated. Written and signed by the notary Ser Jacopo de Uzzano when Lando Salamoncelli of Lucca was podestà. Unbound.
      Part of the Orisini Collection acquired in 1958.
    - Cartulary of Napoleone Orsini, count of Manupello (1353-1370), and his wife Maria da Subiaco. Italy., Collection 902, Box 533 no.ii.; Paper, 219 ff., foliated. In five large quires.; Bound in limp parchment, s. XIV.
      Part of the Orsini Collection acquired in 1958.
    - Giugni family account book, called the Libro grande bianco., 1578-1584; Collection 902, Box 6.; Paper, 193 ff.; 400 × 310 mm. Written by Andrea di Raffaello Giugni in Tuscany, presumably at Garbo. Contemporary thick tooled hide envelope binding, with 5 straps.
      A part of the Corsini Collection, which came to UCLA after World War II. See the Giugni account book described above, Charles E. Young Research Library, Collection 952, Box 1.
  - Department of Special Collections, Manuscripts Bound in Early Printed Books (excluding pastedowns and flyleaves).
    - St. Bernard of Clairvaux, Sermones. Italy., s. XV.; A1 B456 1495.; Paper, 30 ff. Written by one person in a well-formed humanistic script.; Bound in contemporary blind stamped calf over wooden boards, rebacked. Front and back flyleaves: Antiphonal, Italy, s. XIII.
      Bound following Bernardus Claravallensis, Opuscula, ed. Theophilus Brixianus, Venice: Simon Brevilaqua, 1495.
      Erased ex libris: “... de ordine predicatorum.” “Emptus Jeremia die... iulii 1649.”
      Acquired from Bennett Gilbert in 1984.
    - Anon., Commentary on Terence, Adelphoe, lines 237/38-256. Italy., s. XV2; A1 D621v 1475.; Parchment, 1 bifolium, written by one person in an italic hand.; Bound in contemporary Italian black goatskin over beech boards with geometrical tooling. On f. 1, “N. Sig. principe Zuan Maria Baldana” (s. XVex), “Laus Deo 13 luglio 1666,” “Lucretii Palladii 1670,” and an effaced ex libris note.
      From an unbound quire. Pen drawing in the margin: bearded man with helmet in profile. Pastedown (lifted) of Diogenes Laertius, Vitae et sententiae philosophorum, Venice: Nicolas Jenson, 1475.
      Belonged to C.S. Ascherson (bookplate).
      Acquired by J.R. Abbey (leather book label and pen note on rear flyleaf “J.A. 2746 22 I 1946”); his sale Sotheby's 25 June 1965 to UCLA.
    - Lives of Vespasian and Titus Caesar. Italy., s. XV2; *A1 J83d 1486.; Paper (watermark similar to Briquet no.5954 Eclume), 12 ff. Written by one person in an Italian gothic textualis.
      Bound from an early date following Flavius Josephus, De antiquitate Judaica, De bello Judaico, Venice: Joannes Rubeus, 1486.
      Ex libris f. i, “Ad usum Joannis Baptistae Olivae, Juris utriusque Doctoris Patavini et amicorum MDLXI.” Belonged to D.A. Cruse (bookplate).
    - Saints' Lives. Germany., s. XVex; *A1 T36su.; Paper, 8 ff.; Bound in nineteenth-century quarter leather over paper boards.
      Lives of Sts. Kunegunde, Henry II, and Boniface. Written by John of Francis in Mainz or Bamberg after 1481 (colophon, “per me Johannes (sic) Francisci... Moguntie in ecclesia Egidii et Constancie”).
      Bound following Thomas Aquinas, Super quarto libra sententiarum Petri Lombardi, Venice: Johannes Herbort for Nicolas Jenson, 1481.
      Belonged to the Jesuit College at Mainz (ex libris: “Liber Collegii Moguntini Societatis Jesu”). Passed to the Jesuits of Buren in Prussia by the early eighteenth century (ex libris: “Collegii Societatis Jesu Burena anno 1728”). Sold at Parke Bernet 12 November ca. 1930 lot 416 (catalog notice). Belonged to Robert Walsingham Martin (bookplate).
      Acquired from L. Witten in 1981.
    - Computistical Collectanea. Germany., s. XVmed; BV4209 S97 1508.; Paper, 48 ff.; Bound in contemporary plain leather over wooden boards with pastedowns from two manuscripts.
      Bound following Johannes Surgant, Manuale curatorum, Basel: M. Furter. 1508.
      Belonged to Anthonius Wakers (Walhers?) (ex libris on the flyleaf of the printed book: “Codex huius possessor est dominus Anthonius Wakers ...[?] 1556 anno” and his monogram AW). Signature on title page “Iohannes Bonvin,” s. XVII.
      Acquired with the Isaac Foot library in 1962.
    - Cookbook (recipes in German). Germany., s. XVImed; A 1 H655b 1477; Paper, 33 ff.; Bound in contemporary stamped parchment over boards with front and rear pastedowns from a German liturgical manuscript, s. XVI.
      Bound after Charles IV, Bulla aurea, Venice: Nicolas Jenson, 1477; and Von allen Speisen und Gerichten, Augsburg: Heinrich Stayner, 1530.
      The 30 folios of recipes in German are an addition to the printed cookbook.
      Early modern provenance unknown. Belonged to the count of Wolkenstein and Trostberg (bookplate).
      Acquired in 1985.
    - Victor Gislain, Dedicatory preface to an edition of Prudentius addressed to Hippolyte Estense, and a second to Lucas Fruter. Belgium., ca. 1564; PA6648 P6A17 1527.; Paper, 12 ff.
      Gislain, a Flemish humanist, edited ancient authors ca. 1560-1643. Apparently Gislain's copy, being prepared for a new edition which never appeared, since no edition of Prudentius by Gislain is known.
      Bound in Prudentius, Opera omnia, Basel: A. Cratander, 1527.
      Belonged to R.P. Joseph Varesi (”ex libris Josephi Varesi S. Sacre Vaticane Basilice canonici dei 3 Augusti 1755-1760”). From the library of Isaac Foot.
      Acquired with the Foot collection in 1962.
    - Dante col sito, et forma dell 'inferno tratta dalla istessa descritione del poeta (Venice: Aldus Manutius). Italy., s. XVImed (1515); *Z233 A4T34.; Bound in red morocco gilt tooled, s. XVII.
      With extensive manuscript annotations by the Florentine humanist Piero Vettori 1499-1585 who owned this book.
      Belonged to Karl Freiherr Toffholz von Colberg H.H. Hauptmann (book plate).
      Acquired from Salloch in 1983.